דף Daf is מ"ד Mem Daled 44. We pick up on the
משנה Mishna on מ"ג עמוד ב', Mem Gimmel Amud Bais, the second
to
last משנה, Mishna, about eight lines down. We've been talking about the
מומים Mumim of a כהן Kohen as opposed to the מומים Mumim
of a בכור, Bechor, and mentioned that there are three categories: classic
מום Mum which makes the עבודה Avoda invalid, and even there there
are distinctive aspects of humans from animals; and then what seems to
be how the גמרא Gemara has basically framed pretty much our entire
פרק, Perek, which is the ways in which a whole new category,
which is אינו שוה בזרעו של אהרן, Eino Shaveh B'zaro Shel Aharon,
not an actual blemish or disfigurement, but somebody that doesn't fall within
like the once, like I'm calling it the one standard deviation, like
within the middle of the bell-shaped curve. And then still there the
question is what characteristic are we looking at? And then finally a
more minor category are Rabbinic; there the עבודה Avoda isn't invalid, the
גמרא Gemara says it's most an עשה. Aseh. And then you have
a Rabbinic idea of מראית עין Maris Ayin of just appearances which
distracts people, but it's really neither of the above. So I want
before we start reading just to address some interesting questions that arose
yesterday that will lead to a lot more questions, but let's try
to just keep this quick. But I think it's important conceptually. First
of all, a question that didn't arise but is interesting in terms
of the רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם Rambam does not, thank you, the
רמב"ם Rambam actually does not use the phrase of אינו שוה בזרעו
של אהרן. Eino Shaveh B'zaro Shel Aharon. The רמב"ם Rambam actually calls,
like our משניות Mishnayos do, this whole other category, he also calls
it a מום, Mum, a blemish. And the way he describes why
it's distinctive is he just said, well, it's primarily, it's primarily for
either for humans or occurs in humans and not in animals. So
the רמב"ם Rambam really makes it sound like it's just a type
of a blemish which maybe just isn't as shared between humans and
animals. He actually says you're also עובר Over on a לא תעשה,
Lo Sa'aseh, you do transgress, anybody with a blemish cannot serve. So
the רמב"ם Rambam actually does conceptualize it as a blemish and the
only difference for the רמב"ם, Rambam, and not this new idea of
זרעו של אהרן, Zaro Shel Aharon, and the only difference is that
the עבודה Avoda is not מחולל. Mechulal. So that fits more with
the language of the משנה Mishna but is again against how the
גמרא Gemara really reconceptualizes what it seems in terms of us is
really a very larger and different type of a category, not about
blemish. That's just one side point. But other things that were brought
up which are important are number one, you know, the whole question
about the issue here about aesthetics and about the need in like
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So the very good question was raised:
what's the story about a בעל מום Baal Mum and the במה?
Bama? And unfortunately not fitting in with my theory,
the גמרא Gemara in זבחים ק"ז עמוד א' Zevachim 107 Amud Aleph
actually does say that a בעל מום Baal Mum on a במה
Bama is פסול, Pasul, is not valid. There's only one גמרא, Gemara,
there's nothing against it. There's a תוספתא, Tosefta, but the תוספתא Tosefta
could be understood to be referring to a בעל מום Baal Mum
in a קרבן. Korban. But the גמרא Gemara in זבחים Zevachim says
that a כהן Kohen with, not a כהן, Kohen, you don't even
need a כהן, Kohen, even a non-כהן Kohen serves on a במה,
Bama, but a בעל מום Baal Mum is still a
problem, which for the person, right, which again, which exactly, which doesn't
fit so much the whole point about the aesthetics of the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Now it becomes an aesthetics of the same way
the קרבן Korban needs it, anybody who's doing it, like an implicit,
you know, it could be an internalized aesthetic that we just have
about what's appropriate, but again, it doesn't fit so well with my
theory. Two other comments and then I'll take one or two questions
and then we'll actually start reading the גמרא. Gemara. The other two
comments are the following about the issue about, well, it's really the
flip side of the same point, which is Michael asked about things
that are sort of moral issues, you know, people that are known
sinners and so on, is that a problem? Is it to be
just a question about physical aesthetics? So that is the only place
that comes up is by a כהן Kohen who is עובד עבודה
זרה, Oved Avoda Zara, who is פסול Pasul both, who is פסול,
Pasul, but that's because it's עבודה זרה Avoda Zara and it completely
sort of recategorizes the כהן. Kohen.
And, and the גמרא Gemara says that a כהן Kohen who committed
murder cannot actually, even if he's done תשובה Teshuva presumably, cannot be
נושא את כפיו. Nosei Es Kapav. It doesn't mention it for normal
עבודה, Avoda, but that has to do with the emphasis on the
ידיים, Yadayim, ידיכם דמים מלאו, Yadeichem Damim Male'u, like the hands are
bloody hands figuratively. But as a general rule, you know, the moral
issues are not relevant, it's purely the aesthetics. And then in terms
of the question about the difference for נשיאת כפיים, Nesias Kapayim, and
here really it heightens the question about whether it's a concept of
a מום Mum or whether it's an issue about people being distracted.
For נשיאת כפיים Nesias Kapayim there's nothing that has to do with
actual blemishes, you know, it defined in any way on the body,
whatever. The entire concern is things that will distract people. So therefore
it's only the part that's very visible, like things that are on
the hands or in the face of the כהנים, Kohanim, the part
that the people see. And there even are exceptions, like if people
are familiar with this guy in the town and they're used to
whatever his issue is, so then it's not a problem. So for
ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim it is not a formal הלכה, Halacha, it's
completely a question about what is going to distract people. An example
of this would be if a כהן Kohen doesn't pronounce things well,
right, when, when, then anything that can be distracting. distracting and they
also can be mitigated by the fact that people are used to
it where and not an actual blemish, whereas by the עבודה Avoda
it's totally about a blemish and not about a degree of distraction.
So that really seems to get to the issue about, you know,
whether it's just a concern about people's experience, or whether there's something
objective. So my whole nice little explanation that it's about aesthetics does
not really carry through fully, you know, it works more a little
bit more for the ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim but given that it
applies both to a במה Bama and you have this point of
distinction, it does not really work so well. So there you go,
but I don't know how much you can do with that. I
will say by the way if you want to know how many
blemishes there are, the רמב״ם Rambam counts them all and he tells
you all of them and there are he gives you one hundred
and forty blemishes for humans. So I don't know how he manages
to get to that big of a list. Two quick questions and
then we're going to go on here.
How about a במה Bama for a non-Jew which could even be
this day?
Aha,
okay, I'll have to get back to you about that one.
Because the spectrum maybe we're going to talk about is being a
leftie in this?
Yes, coming up. Okay, so now let's take a look there you
go very quick questions. Okay let's take a look now. משנה Mishna
מ״ג עמוד ב׳ Mem Gimmel Amud Bais about ten lines down. אין
לו גבינים Ein lo gavinim if a person does not have eyebrows
או אין לו אלא גבין אחד o ein lo ela gavin echad
or only one eyebrow which רש״י Rashi says it could mean only
over one eye it fell out but anyway רש״י Rashi says it
means like there's a continuous eyebrow over both eyes. Okay, זהו גיבן,
zehu giben,
that's the גיבן giben mentioned in the תורה Torah that the eyebrows
are different. רבי דוסא אומר Rebbi Dosa omer which presumably would make
it an actual מום mum and not just the שוה בזרעו של
אהרן. shaveh b'zaro shel Aharon. רבי דוסא אומר Rebbi Dosa omer שגבינים
שוכבין, shegavinim shochvin,
no,
it means that the eyebrows are very long and the hair actually
comes all like comes down significantly. Like they can't be trimmed? Yeah,
it's a good question; maybe as long as they're not trimmed. I
don't know, it's a very good point. Okay, רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס
אומר Rebbi Chanina ben Antignos omer שיש לו שני גבים ושתי שדראות.
sheyesh lo shnei gabim u'shtei shidraos. He doesn't explain
גיבן giben from the word גבינים, gavinim, which is eyebrow, but from
the word גב, gav, back. He has two separate spinal cords or
backbones and two backs. Wow, so that's pretty bizarre like a person
like that could actually live. So let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא's Gemara going to discuss that. They can
live? Yeah.
Wow. It they are
conjoined twins who never got separated. Ha.
So what happens to like what wow. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, הגיבן דאינו משמע. Ha'giben de'eino mashma. גיבן Giben like
you'd think maybe it means like the second explanation maybe the eyebrows
are particularly long. How does the word גיבן giben mean you don't
have an eyebrow? By the way, I mean you have that sometimes
in English too, right, about like that words mean either doesn't or
do, like I always like the example where it says your pistachios
are shelled and salted. Right, shelled means the shells are removed and
salted means that salt is added. So anyway גיבן giben here means
you don't have the eyebrows. Okay. ורמינהי, U'reminhi, גיבן שיש לו גבינים
הרבה. giben sheyesh lo gavinim harbe. So גיבן giben means he has
many eyebrows. אין לו גבינים, Ein lo gavinim, no eyebrows, או אין
לו אלא גבין אחד o ein lo ela gavin echad or only
one, מנין, minayin, תלמוד לומר talmud lomar או גיבן. o giben. So
the word גיבן giben fundamentally means many. The או o is coming
to say or the reverse, which is fewer. So אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, זהו מדרש או גיבן. zehu midrash o giben.
Fine, when the משנה Mishna says this is the גיבן giben in
the תורה Torah it means this is the או גיבן. o giben.
Yeah you're right, it's learned from the extra word או. o. Fine.
רבי דוסא אומר, Rebbi Dosa omer, two separate backs. למימרא דחיה, L'meimra
de'chaya,
it sounds like a person with two backs can live. והתניא, Ve'hatanya,
המפלת שפיר שיש לו שני גבים Ha'mafeles shapir sheyesh lo shnei gabim
if a woman miscarries a fetus that had two backs ושתי שדראות
u'shtei shidraos and two backbones, that she is not טמאה לידה tmeia
leida because because it's not considered to have ever been viable. ואמר
רב, Ve'amar Rav, באשה אינו ולד, be'isha eino valad, it's not even
considered to be a child. בבהמה אסור באכילה Be'veheima assur b'achila and
in an animal you can't eat it presumably even if it's alive
and you שחט shacht it because it's never been considered to actually
have been able to be viable and therefore it's essentially like a
נבילה. neveila.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ורמינהי עליה דרב
שימי בר חייא לרב. U'reminhi alei d'Rav Shimi bar Chiya l'Rav. So
wait, that question already was asked by רב שימי בר חייא Rav
Shimi bar Chiya to רב. Rav. ואמר ליה, Ve'amar lei, רב Rav
said to him, שימי את, Shimi at, you're Shimi? It's a very
funny phrase that the גמרא Gemara there's always debate whether it means
that was an insult or a compliment. Oy, Shimi, such a good
question! Or Shimi, is this a question really worthy of you? Anyway,
אלא בששדרתו עקומה. ela she'shidraso akuma.
So actually here it sounds like a good question because it says
you're right, two separate backs really can never live and therefore we
wouldn't even be discussing it as a מום, mum, and when we
say two backs we don't literally mean two backs, we mean it
looks like two backs. It really means somebody's got a curved back,
a bent spine. So something like that and that's what we're talking
about. You have a problem Charlie, too much of a misreading of
the משנה? Mishna?
No, no, it's not factually correct.
We don't mean that technology whatever and science would never develop to
the point that that person could live.
Yeah, you'd be surprised that the תורה Torah at least according to
this
explanation, you'd think if there were two heads they would have mentioned
it and the גמרא Gemara the way I'd imagine it. Interesting.
Wait, so you're saying this is one person with one head and
two backs or just...
Yeah, well and the answer that our משנה, Mishna, no, it's just
a bent back.
The משנה Mishna the way they explain it is just one back
but it's bent.
No, I'm saying the one in... where it says שני גבים ושתי
שדראות. shnei gavim u'shnei shidra'ot. Yeah,
so
it's this person has one head and two backs or just two...
No, so the end we said it doesn't literally mean two, it
means it looks like two, it really just means a bent over
back. I see. So that's you know which makes it anyway more
understandable. Okay, but it doesn't sound like it from the משנה. Mishna.
Okay, so that's the גיבן. giben. Now...
I'm sorry, so you're saying שני גבים ושתי שדראות shnei gavim u'shnei
shidra'ot so the back is so bent it looks like he has
two backs? Two spines?
Something like that, that's how you'd have to read it. It's so
bent that it looks like two.
Because I was going to say that it's folded over. Right, exactly.
For the תורה Torah to go out of the way to describe
something so out of the pale, they could have said what about
the person with like five legs?
Yeah, yeah, I understand, I understand. By the way, I should tell
you...
it's a מום, mum, correct.
All right, yeah, I get it. By the way, the רמב"ם Rambam
says in משנה תורה Mishneh Torah he says the list of the
תורה Torah he says these are just examples. Like you know...
Not 140, it's even more.
No, no, no, he didn't say the תורה's Torah list had 140,
his list was not just examples, his list was exhaustive, but he
says don't give special weight to the ones mentioned in the תורה,
Torah, the תורה Torah was just giving these as a couple of
examples and you figure out the rest. All right, let's look at
the next משנה. Mishna.
החרום פסול. Ha-charum pasul. Now, או חרום o charum is another case
in the תורה. Torah. איזהו חרום? Eizu charum? What's a חרום? charum?
So, שחוטמו שבין עיניו כאחת. she-chotmo she-bein einav k'achat. That you don't
have the bridge of your nose between the eyes and therefore you
can basically put eyeshadow on two eyes without it being interrupted with
any barrier. Okay, so basically you don't have it or it's completely
inset.
Now, שתי עיניו למעלה ושתי עיניו למטה. shtei einav l'ma'ala u'shtei einav
l'mata. If your eyes are placed in your skull in places that
they would not normally be, they're particularly high up or they're particularly
low down. עינו אחת למעלה ועינו אחת למטה. eino achat l'ma'ala v'eino
achat l'mata. One is high and one is low. Or רואה את
החדר ואת העלייה כאחת. ro'eh et hachadar v'et ha'aliya k'echad. Or your
eyes are at the same physical level but you're cross-eyed that basically
one eye looks up and the other eye looks down. Okay, so
they're physically in your skull in the right place but they look
in wrong places. סכיף שמש. Sachif shemesh. Or somebody that is particularly
sensitive to the sun, cannot bear really even be in direct sunlight
or certainly look at the sun. What? Albinos are that way? Interesting.
Is it only albinos? Because you'd think if it's albino you'd think
it would also mention that. Some people have light sensitivity. I think
some people even without albinos just have particularly sensitive eyes.
We had didn't say two different color eyes. הזגדן והצירן. Ha-zagdan v'ha-tziran.
And the הזגדן zagdan and the הצירן, tziran, the גמרא Gemara will
discuss this so I won't. And שנשרו ריסי עיניו פסול מפני מראית
העין. she-nashru risei einav pasul mipnei mar'it ayin. If the eyelashes fell
out, that's invalid because
of how it looks, so it's only rabbinic but it's not a
real מום mum and it's not even a real problem of a
זר שארע. zar she-ara. The גמרא Gemara before said that this last
line מפני מראית העין mipnei mar'it ayin could go how far back
that's explaining, maybe the whole משנה, Mishna, but the גמרא Gemara emphasized
that that was only explaining right, so it couldn't really go back
beyond חרום charum is probably correct. Anyway, but the גמרא Gemara said
before it's only explaining the very last case. Perfect specimen.
Right. Could there have been so many כהנים? Kohanim? Right. With no
teeth, no skin problems, the head shape is right. Right. Most people,
right. Most people have some little...
Yeah, but some little thing
that falls under
these?
I don't know. You look at a normal room of 100 people,
how many would you find that would have any one of these?
I don't know. It must occur in less than 1% of the
population.
But I don't think the problem is how many people you're excluding,
I think the challenge is you know the whole approach of like
perfection, right? And especially you know like what we've been discussing from
a religious perspective, the idea of perfection should be more about the
person, the character, the soul, not about the physical. So you know
I said I think this is related to particular issue of aesthetics,
but I just mention at the beginning
why that doesn't exactly fit you know what we have found in
terms of the scope of it. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, חרום שחוטמו שקוע. charum she-chotmo shaku'a.
That his nose is depressed, it's pushed down. חוטמו סולד חוטמו בולם.
chotmo soled, chotmo bolen.
How about other things? Like for example if it is a very...
it's not the bridge but like it's you know it's very narrow,
sort of flat, a flat nose. Or it is a sealed nose,
a fused nose. How you'd breathe without your nostrils. חוטמו נוטף Hotamo
notef or apparently some condition of a permanently dripping nose. מניין? Minayin?
תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: או חרום. O charum. So the או O
includes any problem with the nose and this is considered a real
מום. mum. At the end of the day how you know these
things particularly like the dripping nose or whatever I mean some of
the things that are a real מום mum seem less severe than
some of the things that are considered to be like only this
זרעו של אהרן zaro shel Aharon category. So I really cannot conceptually
explain all the
eyes of the nose.
No the eyes was גיבן. giben.
No like oh no
no that's what was done because of the nose.
You can call it the
eyes because of the nose. Yeah but that was a nose. One
eye above one eye below. Yeah no that wasn't חרום. charum.
Oh it's not חרום? charum? So wait so what's חרום charum going
on?
On the nose problem. רבי יוסי אומר אין חרום אלא הכוחל שתי
עיניו כאחת. Rabbi Yossi omer ein charum ela hakocha shtei einav ke'achas.
No it's only the only case is when the nose is so
depressed that you can paint both eyes with at once. אמרו לו
Amru lo they said to him הפלגת hiflagta you've exaggerated. It doesn't
need to be that big of a problem. אף על פי שאינו
כוחל שתי עיניו כאחת Af al pi she'eino kocha shtei einav ke'achas
even if it's depressed without that point that there's absolutely no barrier.
That you don't need it to reach that extreme. Okay שעיניו למעלה
שעיניו למטה. she'einav lemala she'einav lemata. Now the eyes that are in
different locations. מאי שעיניו למעלה שעיניו למטה? Mai she'einav lemala she'einav lemata?
What does it mean that they're either both above or both below?
אילימא שעיניו למעלה דחזי למעלה Ileima she'einav lemala dechazi lemala it doesn't
mean their physical location is different it means where they're looking that
the eyes are constantly looking up or שעיניו למטה דחזי למטה she'einav
lemata dechazi lemata
they're constantly looking down.
So ואינו אחת למעלה ואינו אחת למטה ve'eino achat lemala ve'eino achat
lemata so one above one below means דחזי עינו אחת למעלה ועינו
אחת למטה dechazi eino achat lemala ve'eino achat lemata one eye looks
up and one eye looks down. So no that can't be that
we're just talking about where they're looking because at the end of
the משנה mishna it says היינו רואה את החדר ואת העליה hayinu
ro'eh et hachadar ve'et ha'aliya that you want that one looks at
the one is looking at the room and the other is looking
at the attic. So the end of the משנה mishna discusses the
different places they're looking. So the beginning of the משנה mishna is
not where they're looking but where they're actually physically located. So the
גמרא gemara says אלא ela okay fine here's how you have to
read the משנה mishna not where they're looking but where they are
located in the skull. שעיניו למעלה דקיימי למעלה she'einav lemala dekayimi lemala
both eyes are situated high up in the skull. שעיניו למטה דקיימי
למטה she'einav lemata dekayimi lemata they're lower in the skull than they
would normally be. עינו אחת למעלה ועינו אחת למטה eino achat lemala
ve'eino achat lemata one up and one below דקיימי עינו אחת למעלה
ועינו אחת למטה dekayimi eino achat lemala ve'eino achat lemata one is
too high and the other is too low or relatively low they're
in different places.
Now and also so besides just situated
incorrectly דקיימי כסדרן נמי dekayimi kesidran nami and even if they're the
right place ורואה החדר ואת העליה vero'eh hachadar ve'et ha'aliya but if
they look in opposite places they're like cross-eyed. Like a cross-eyed really
means you're like looking like that right? Is there a word for
like just looking like what's it called like wandering eye or something?
What's that called?
Lazy eye or something? That's different. Okay anyway so but if they
look if one looks up and the other looks down that's also
a problem. So now והא נמי מנא הני מילי? veha nami menal
hanei milei? Where is this from? Right this is not nose problems
which is חרום charum this is eye problems. So where's this from?
תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: בעינו. be'eino. Remember it said או דק או
תבלול בעינו. o dak o tavlul be'eino. So דק dak we're going
to see is explained before it came up before but we didn't
really analyze the פסוקים psukim as much in the last פרק perek
which means like some type of a film across the eye like
a cataracts or something. תבלול Tavlul we've said was that like white
streaks that goes from the white of the eye into the pupil.
And now we're going to say the fact that it says בעינו
be'eino somehow from context I would have understood that those words meant
eye problems. So the fact that the תורה torah added the word
בעינו be'eino we're going to learn symbolizes any eye issue even not
limited to these two.
כל מה שבעינו. Kol ma shebe'eino. We're going to see actually in
a minute that we're going to conceptually have different categories about that.
Anything regarding the eyes. מכאן אמרו: Mikan amru: שעיניו למטה שעיניו למעלה
she'einav lemata she'einav lemala either both high or both low עינו אחת
למעלה ועינו אחת למטה eino achat lemala ve'eino achat lemata one high
one low ורואה החדר ורואה העליה vero'eh hachadar vero'eh ha'aliya or one
looks at the room and one looks at the attic. They look
in different places. כאחת או Ke'achas o here's another variation of looking
in the wrong direction שמדבר עם חברו ואחר אומר לי אומר לי
רואה. shemedaber im chavero ve'acher omer li omer li ro'eh.
You're looking at somebody and you're talking to somebody and some guy
over there says you're looking at me. So you know even if
you're pointing forward this eye is sort of that might be the
lazy I don't know is that lazy eye? Whatever it is anyway
your eyes are not tracking the same way. Okay so one minute.
So תנו רבנן tanu rabanan now we're going to see where we
get different conceptual categories a very nice גמרא gemara here that's going
to conceptually create categories. עיור Iver blind.
בין סומא בשתי עיניו Bein suma bishtei einav whether somebody does not
have sight in both eyes בין סומא באחת מעיניו bein suma be'achat
mei'einav or only no sight in one eyes. חיורר והמים הקבועים Chivrar
vehamayim hakevu'im remember that by the animals? Which were the dots in
the eyes or
regular non-ceasing dripping water from the eye. מניין? Minayin? תלמוד לומר: Talmud
lomar: איש עיור Ish iver the word איש ish okay
is coming to include even other cases that are like that. And
apparently those problems cause a blurriness of vision or only partial vision.
So it's similar to blind not that there's no vision out of
the eye but it is. is decreased vision.
Unless you just have very bad eyesight.
Well, no. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, correct. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, ולמה
לי דכתב רחמנא v'lamah li d'khata rachamana איש עיוור, ish iver, דק,
dak, תבלול בעינו? tavlul b'eino? Why do you need all those categories?
Blind, דק dak which is like a cataract, תבלול tavlul is the
mixing of the white cutting into the pupil. צריכי, Tzerikhi, you need
all those categories.
דאי כתב רחמנא De'i khata rachamana עיוור, iver, blind, משום דלית ליה
כלל, mishum d'leit lei klal, there's no sight. אבל חורור, Aval khurvar,
whatever,
והמים הקבועים, v'hamayim hakvuim, וספץ, v'spatz, and the watery, דאיתנהו ביה, d'itnehu
bei, that you do have some sight out of the eye, לא,
lo, maybe that would not be included. כתב רחמנא Khata rachamana איש,
ish, that איש ish which is an extra word, which means even
if it's a similar problem, it's blurry vision or it's limited vision
even though it's no vision. ואי כתב רחמנא V'i khata rachamana איש,
ish, even if it had limited to the cases of the blindness,
then משום דלא חזי כלל, mishum d'lo khazi klal, because it's actual
no vision, it's limited vision. Now by the way, Rashi says I've
been explaining it a little bit differently. Rashi says that in the
cases of the watery eye whatever you actually don't see out of
the eye at all, but it's different from עיוור iver that the
eye is physically present. And in these cases the ספץ spatz and
the watery, you might not see for it is physically present but
you still don't see from it at all. I'm not sure if
you have to say that in the גמרא. Gemara. You could say
that it's a degree of blindness, not total blindness but still decreased
and partial vision. Anyway, that's what I would have said by the
עיוור iver category,
that it has to do with no vision or maybe partial vision
the way I'm reading it. Now, אבל מחסוריתא, Aval makhasurita, לא, lo,
but maybe if it's sort of, this is why Rashi says that
case was no vision, because now it says if it's however lacking,
like it is the vision but it's lacking vision, maybe that wouldn't
be a problem. כתב רחמנא Khata rachamana דק, dak, דק dak which
is the film or the cataracts. Okay, now I still think there
could be difference, like one is like a blurry vision, right, which
you can imagine by a film as opposed to like diminished vision
which is only like...
maybe you can't see out of the particular spot where you have
the spot. Maybe as opposed to a film where they can see
throughout, hopefully.
Okay, it could be. Anyway, you have one category which has no
vision or very limited vision, and another category of דק dak which
I would say is more has to do with like blurry vision.
Okay, so that's a different conceptual category. ואי כתב רחמנא V'i khata
rachamana דק, dak, had it just said דק, dak, which is this
film, משום דמחסרן, mishum d'makhasran, that's because it actually, yes, your vision
is lacking, it's blurry. אבל מבולבלייתא, Aval mivulbalita, but if it's just
that the eye is somehow, you know, mixed up, meaning like
aesthetically, לא, lo, כתב רחמנא Khata rachamana תבלול tavlul which is the
white streak which actually, you know, separates the different segments of the
eye, it mixes them up but maybe doesn't affect the vision at
all. ואי כתב רחמנא V'i khata rachamana תבלול, tavlul, if it had
just said תבלול, tavlul, משום דמבלבלן, mishum d'mivulbalan, because it's mixed up.
אבל משום משנייתא, Aval mishum mishniyata, but if it just were different
without actually the eyeball being, you know, the boundaries being disturbed, being
sort of
crossed, לא, lo, כתב רחמנא Khata rachamana בעינו, b'eino, in your eye,
which basically means one high and one low or looking in different
places. Now I should point out by the way that this idea
of if I would have just said this I wouldn't have applied
it to here, right, you know, sort of also challenges the whole
idea of it all being about aesthetics. Because, you know, certainly the
thing that's probably the biggest aesthetic problem is if you've got one
eye up and one eye down or you have two eyes way
up high here where they shouldn't be. I mean that's very, you
know, as opposed to a person that has let's say a cataract
in the eye, who can even see that? That you have a
cataract, I mean maybe it's somewhat visible but a lot of these
things, right, are things which are not as visible. And the גמרא
Gemara said well but they're bigger problems because you know they actually
have no vision or very decreased vision. So it again raises this
question of how to exactly conceptually define מום mum if the fact
of lacking vision is more of a problem than, you know, than
something that's clearly aesthetically problematic. But all of these things are at
least somewhat visible. I mean somebody that just has poor vision, right,
presumably
is not visible at all, the fact that the person has that
problem. Okay, so now let's see what the גמרא Gemara says, and
what the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara wraps this up.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, הלכך, hilkhakh, therefore, כל מחמת כיהותא kol makhamat
kihuta אתא מאיש. ata mi-ish. Anything that has to do with sort
of decreased vision, weak vision, again the question is would that be
just because a person has bad eyesight or does it actually mean
some type of a physical ailment which causes that? That's from the
word איש, ish, איש עיוור, ish iver, not just pure blind but
even partial blindness. מחסוריתא, Makhasurita,
lacking vision, which I think probably means blurry vision, מדק, mi-dak, from
the דק dak which is like the film. מבולבלייתא, Mivulbalita, the eye,
the pupil itself, the eyeball itself is somehow is mixed up, it
does not have the normal sort of segment, מתבלול, mi-tavlul, from the
word תבלול. tavlul. משנייתא, Mishniyata,
different, that the eyes are in the different places than they normally
would be or looking different, differently, they're not tracking equally, מבעינו, mi-b'eino,
you learn that from בעינו. b'eino. So you have a couple of
very different categories, but again interesting about how it's not all just
about... purely about aesthetic. What was the case?
What was the case? You said כל מחמת כיסה?
kol machmanas keisah? So רש"י Rashi says it means actually no blindness
at all. I say it means diminished sight as opposed to as
opposed to דק dak which I would say means blurry sight. That's
the difference between blurry and diminished. It's a good question.
One is, what about people, and I actually know people like this,
that have different color eyes? Is that not a problem?
Yeah, that's interesting. The גמרא Gemara is going to get to that.
Let's take, the גמרא Gemara is actually going to get to that
in one second.
And I've actually been pondering for a while because you know talking
about like the you know sort of like a depressed nose bridge,
a nose bridge. What about Asians? You know like that that that
you know their nose, the bridge of their nose is you know
a lot lower over here and they probably could go you know
חוטמו שקועה כאחת? chotmo shekuah ke-achas? Yes,
right?
In contemplation. Yeah, it's very common over here.
Wow. That's very interesting. Right. Yeah. Ha. Well, let's try to remember
that because we're going to come up to a משנה Mishna that
actually talks about different races. Okay, so let's let's think about that
then. Now, it doesn't frame it the way you're doing because let's
say because of a different race you have one of these things
but it has to but it's a racial characteristic. The גמרא Gemara
later is going to talk about races that themselves are let's say
you know other other things that are distinctive about them and would
that be considered, how that would be considered. So it's a good
question. Let's revisit that when we get to the yeah when we
get to the discussion about races, believe me it's going to be
it's going to be an interesting enough discussion there but let's try
to remember that.
Though yes, what about some of these vision issues, anybody who wears
glasses?
Right, like the fact that we see that you're wearing glasses makes
it you know you know and the fact that you know people
you know they they they basically if you have really bad vision
you know it's pretty clear by the way you're navigating the world
that you've got some issue. Right, I mean if a cataract's at
דק, dak, I mean I mean that's why the גמרא Gemara was
always an example about the גמרא Gemara about the hardest מום mum
to notice is that it's so דק. dak. But let's say sunglasses?
No, wasn't that Ben Franklin? Yeah, he invented bifocals.
Oh, he invented bifocals.
Oh, there was
no such thing back then.
I know. I know. You really do wonder how Jews survived for
thousands of years before glasses were invented. Besides, I know, it it
really is it really is an interesting question about it clearly is
more than just the aesthetics here. All right, anyway let's take a
look. סכי שמש, sachi shemesh, very sensitive to the sun. תני רב
יוסף. tani Rav Yosef. Now again, that's also a good example, sensitive
to the sun. Is that visible by looking at the person? It's
only visible by the person being outdoors, right?
Or maybe I was going to say that, yeah, רב יוסף Rav
Yosef was blind. What? רב יוסף? Rav Yosef?
רב יוסף Rav Yosef was blind. שגיא נהור. sagi nahor. No, רב
יוסף Rav Yosef also. Okay, סני שמש, sani shemesh, it's interesting the
point that he's got. So somebody that hates the sun, meaning can't
be outdoors. Okay, but again, it's not visible you know noticeable by
just physically looking at the person. It's only noticeable when they step
outside. What? Red hair? Red hair, yeah.
Okay, זגדיין. zagdayan. Now what's this זגדיין? zagdayan? מחוי רב הונא. machvei
Rav Huna. רב הונא Rav Huna indicated חד מדידן וחד מדידהו, chad
mididan ve-chad mididehu, one of ours and one of his eyes. And
who's the his? So apparently the the his is רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda who was standing was in front of him. So he basically
meant like somebody would have one of my eyes and one of
his eyes. ואיקפיד רב יהודה ve-ikpid Rav Yehuda and רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, I will tell you, and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was offended.
So what does that mean? So רש"י Rashi just says their eyes
looked different. But תוספות Tosafos says actually it's unclear. תוספות Tosafos actually
says he proves from other גמרות, Gemaros, it's like fascinating how the
תוספות Tosafos was able to identify, I mean whatever, obviously תוספות, Tosafos,
that you know one גמרא Gemara that indicated that רב הונא Rav
Huna was a small was a slightly smaller man and רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda was a larger man. So basically it means misshapen eyes,
like one small eye and one big eye. And רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda was offended, like why point him out as somebody that like
oh look like you know like an extra big eye like him.
Like you know people don't like making personal comments about them. So
anyway, but the basic point is eyes that are you know that
they're not in themselves particularly small or particularly big, but relative to
one another they are not paired. Okay, now we're going to get
to the issue about paired. So let's take a look.
מיתיבי, meisivei, I'll ask from this. שכבנו, shichvano, what does that mean?
שזה לא, she-zeh lo, that's not a case in the תורה Torah
but a rabbinic term. שגביניו שוכבין, she-gevinav shochvin, that the eyebrows are
you know very long hair and they go on top of they
go cover over the eye. זגדום, zagdum, now that was a case
in our משנה, Mishna, right? Our משנה Mishna said זגדן, zagdan, so
this is now זגדום zagdum as it appears here. So אחד שחור
ואחד לבן. echad shachor ve-echad lavan. There you go, Michael, one black
and one white. Now it's a little funny since when are the
irises black and white? Right? So but anyway, but it does seem
to mean any pair that does not work, that does not that
does not combine. So תוספות Tosafos by the way, now the שיטה
מקובצת Shita Mekubetzes says זגדום שגביניו אחד, zagdum she-gevinav echad, that his
eyebrows, but we probably it could just be we're talking about the
pupil, no the eyebrows are different colors. But we could just be
talking about the fact that the pupils, by the way תוספות Tosafos
says that this actually is a word because
זוג... zug... is the Rabbinic word for pair, and he says it's
not זגדום Zagdum but what often happens when we have Greek transliterations
is the סמך Samech becomes a מם Mem and because as a
מם Mem is a more normal ending letter for Hebrew words but
a סמך Samech more for Greek words or an S, so זגדות,
Zagdos, dos is deuce, deuce which is two. So a pair, two,
but it really means a non-paired pair, like that they're not equally
paired. Okay? So תנא כל זוגא, Tana kol zuga, so anyway, so
you see that it says white and black, it doesn't say big
and small. So how do you say it means big and small?
So the גמרא Gemara generalizes it. תנא כל זוגא דלא שוי להדדי,
Tana kol zuga delo shavi lahadadi, any pair where they're not equally
paired, זגדות Zagdos or זגדום Zagdum קרי ליה. karei leh. Now the
question is again, would that apply to all limbs or just particularly
the eyes? The eyes are more higher up in the head and
more visible. We're going to see a משנה Mishna in a minute
that is going to talk about non-equally paired limbs. Okay, so that,
but
yes?
I am trying to understand, so because remember when we have קרבנות
korbanot we said one is like גדול של עגל gadol shel egel
the other is קטן של ענבה. katan shel anava.
We're going to get that in the next משנה.
Mishna. So but here we're saying it doesn't have to be that
way, it means even if they're not...
right. But that's when they are paired but they're either particularly big
or particularly small.
Here they are not paired, they are disproportionate one to the other.
Right, that's why he said like one small eye and one big
eye. Yes, as within people they fall within the normal range, but
if you get, you know, disproportionate limbs in the same person, that's
a מום. mum.
Yes, so regarding eyeglasses, magnification was known in ancient times, but eyeglasses
themselves were invented in the 13th century in Italy. Wow. Wait, so
that means if you have very bad eyesight you can't serve?
I don't know, all I know is I mean this has people
that are particularly sensitive to the sun. But you know, so the
question is how do you define visible, you know? Alright, so okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: הצירן, hatziran, what's הצירן? hatziran?
עיניו, einav, okay, so now we have a ברייתא: braita: תנא הצירן
עיניו טרוטות וצירניות. Tana hatziran einav trutot vetziraniot. If your eyes are
טרוטות trutot or צירניות. tziraniot. רש"י Rashi says that those words basically
mean circular as opposed to, you know, eye-shaped, they're particularly overly circular.
There's
two different degrees of circularity.
Okay, דומות, dumot, לופות, lofot, צרודות, tzerodot, now this is similar to
the thing we saw before about watery eyes, if they're constantly teary
or לופות lofot is even more that they stream more, צרודות tzerodot
is like they gush out. So תוספות Tosafos says once you say
teary, why do you need the more extreme cases? Okay, תנא, Tana,
he doesn't have an answer. Anyway,
and תוספות Tosafos also says well what he actually says is to
tell you are these again the question always here, are these a
מום mum or are these just a problem of not שוה בזרעו
של אהרן? shaveh be-zaro shel Aharon? The difference whether the עבודה avoda
is not valid or not. So תוספות Tosafos says well maybe we
gave the whole range to tell you even at the narrow end
of the range it's still פסול, pasul, but even at the more
extreme end of the range like constantly flowing it still would only
be a שוה בזרעו של אהרן shaveh be-zaro shel Aharon problem and
not a מום mum problem. That's actually the answer תוספות Tosafos says.
Okay, תנא הזדיר והלופן והתמיר. Tana hazadir vehalufan vehatamir.
So what is that, so what does this mean? So זביר zavir
or זדיר, zadir, דמזיר עיני, demazir einai, that his eyes are מזין
mazir which basically I'm trying to remember what רש"י Rashi says, I
think he means that they're very hairy like the eyelashes go, hold
on, let me just I just forgot.
One minute. Constantly
moving. Constantly moving?
Oh yeah you're right, the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says thank you,
שאינו יכול לנוח ממשוטטות. she'eino yachol lanoach mimshotetot.
Right. So that might be the lazy eye. Your eyes are not,
you know, are constantly moving. Or he says oh or that they're
constantly open,
so some type of a thing that the eyes are like from
the word... okay anyway let's take the first explanation, your eyes are
constantly moving. לופין, lufin, what does לופין lufin mean? דנפישין זיפי, denefishin
zifei, that the eyelashes are very long. תמיר tamir שתמו זיפין shetamu
zifein that you don't have eyelashes. So the גמרא Gemara says והני
גבי מומין תני להו, vehani gabei mumin tani lehu, one minute, is
that ברייתא braita by actual blemish? והתנן vehatnan our משנה Mishna says
שנשרו ריסי עיניו פסול מפני מראית עין, shenashru risei einav pasul mipnei
maris ayin, that no eyelashes is not actually a מום, mum, it's
only this Rabbinic מראית עין. maris ayin. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, לא קשיא. lo kashya. הא דאשתייר גרדומי hai de'ishtayer gardumei
if there's a little bit of the roots of the hair left
then it's only a מראית עין maris ayin problem. הא דלא אשתייר
גרדומי hai delo ishtayer gardumei if none of the roots of the
eyelashes are left, then it's an actual מום. mum. And even there
you have to ask does he really mean מום mum or do
you just mean not שוה בזרעו של אהרן. shaveh be-zaro shel Aharon.
Okay so that is eyelashes and paired eyes, and our משנה Mishna
now we continue with other eye issues.
Let's just take a look... trim the eyebrows.
Yeah so I don't know, maybe it means as long as you
haven't trimmed them. There are some things that are a מום mum
until you... but you can get rid of them. Like what? Well
I mean the ילפת, yalefet, those hair... and we'll see in a
minute some things about a problem about a פרה אדומה. Para Aduma.
This is because I remember like you know this ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish that his were very long.
Right, that's right, that is true. Yeah, maybe it would have been
a מום. mum. Okay we're actually going to talk about... that particular
important figures and whether they had מומים. mumim. So let's take a
look. עיניו גדולות כשל עגל. einav gedolot keshel egel.
Now your eyes are big now this is that the eyes are
paired, they're equal, but they're particularly big or particularly small. So as
big as a calf's, או קטנות כשל אווז o ktanot keshel avaz
or as small as a duck's. So if they're overly big or
overly small. גופו גדול מאיבריו. gufo gadol me'evarav. Now here we go
disproportionate, not the limbs to one and another, but the limbs to
the body. Your body is larger than your limbs. You know there's
a particular
proportion of limbs to the body size, the torso size or whatever,
and this person it's disproportionate. או קטן מאיבריו o katan me'evarav or
his body is smaller proportionally than his limbs. חוטמו גדול מאיבריו chotmo
gadol me'evarav or your nose is bigger than your body than the
other, you know, proportionally to the rest of your limbs. או קטן
מאיבריו o katan me'evarav or proportionally smaller. Now so those are general
issues of proportions. הצומם והצומע. hatzomem vehatzome'a. And also צומם tzomem and
צומע. tzome'a. So what are those? איזהו צומע? eizehu tzome'a? What's a
צומע? tzome'a? כל שאזניו קטנות. kol she'oznav ktanot. They are particularly small
ears. הצומם, hatzomem, כל שאזניו דומות לספוג kol she'oznav domot lisfog
that his ears look like a sponge. There actually is something like
this, right? Called a particular what? Cauliflower. Yeah, cauliflower. Yeah. So that
I think is what it's talking about. שפתיו עליונה עודפת על התחתונה
והתחתונה עודפת על העליונה, sfatov elyonah adefah al hatachtonah vehatachtonah adefah al
ha'elyonah,
if your, you know, your lip protrudes either over your lower lip
or your lower lip from out of your under lip, הרי זה
מום harei zeh mum that is a מום. mum. Now we'll go
again, calls it a מום, mum, the גמרא Gemara earlier said it
was really only a problem, at least one of those was only
a problem of זר שלא אהרון. zar shelo Aharon. So again we
have the idea that the משנה Mishnah is constantly calling things מום,
mum, but the גמרא Gemara has reframed them as being this middle
category of not, you know, not within the sort of middle of
the distribution, but nevertheless not a full blemish. Anyway, and then it
has one more case about מראית עין. mar'it ayin. ושנשרו שיניו, veshenishru
shinav, the eyebrows fell out like the eyebrows fell out possibly, which
happens to people in old
age. Right. פסול מפני מראית עין, pasul mipnei mar'it ayin, that's only
a problem about the visuals. It is not a real מום. mum.
Okay, now let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. By the
way, I have to point out to you a very interesting רש"י.
Rashi. If you look at the רש"י Rashi on the משנה, Mishnah,
צומם צומע, tzomem tzome'a, רש"י Rashi says במתניתין מפרש לה. bamatnitin mefaresh
lah. Right? Usually you read רש"י Rashi on the משנה Mishnah and
he says בגמרא מפרש לה. bagemara mefaresh lah. But here actually the
משנה, Mishnah, the משנה Mishnah explained what those terms mean. But you
also wonder like it was literally the next line of the משנה.
Mishnah. Yeah. So רש"י Rashi had to assume people were reading his
commentary word for word so they didn't even get to the next
line yet. But anyway, it was a very interesting רש"י Rashi because
usually he
says בגמרא מפרש לה.
bagemara mefaresh lah. What?
Is it possible that מראית עין mar'it ayin was added later?
You mean that that wasn't originally part of רש"י. Rashi. Yeah, well
the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet crosses it out. So there might not
have been an original part of רש"י. Rashi.
That's why God gave you two hands and fingers on two.
Exactly. Exactly. Okay.
אמר רב, Amar Rav, משה רבינו עשר אמות היה. Moshe Rabbeinu eser
amot hayah. משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu was ten אמות amot tall.
שנאמר shene'emar ויפרוש את
האוהל, vayifros et ha'ohel, ויפרוש, vayifros, ויפרוש, vayifros, right? ויפרוש את האוהל.
vayifros et ha'ohel. He spread out the אוהל ohel על המשכן al
hamishkan over the משכן, Mishkan, right? The roof of the משכן. Mishkan.
מי פירסו? mi pirso? Who spread it out? משה רבינו פירסו. Moshe
Rabbeinu pirso. משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu did. דכתיב dechtiv עשר אמות אורך
הקרש. eser amot orech hakeresh. How tall were the beams? The beams
were ten אמות amot tall. So to be able to stand, like
when you put out your tablecloth on שבת, Shabbos, you have to
be bigger than the thing that you're spreading it out over. Twelve,
well maybe it means up to his shoulders was ten אמות, amot,
often we don't count the head in that count and what. So
okay. So okay. Anyway, he had to be also super strong because
also how do you get the width of it? And normally you
need somebody else at the other side. Anyway, fine. So alright. אמר
ליה שימי בר חייא לרב, amlei Shimi bar Chiya leRav, אם כן
עשיתו למשה רבינו בעל מום. im ken asita leMoshe Rabbeinu ba'al mum.
So you've made משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu a בעל מום. ba'al mum.
דתנן disnan גופו גדול מאיבריו או קטן מאיבריו. gufo gadol me'evarav o
katan me'evarav. If he's disproportionate. Why are we saying he's disproportionate? Because
we're assuming that if you're mentioning an אמה, amah, that the קרש
keresh was an אמה, amah, it's an אמה amah is an arm's
length of משה's Moshe arm's length. So therefore you're saying that משה's
Moshe height was ten times, was ten אמות amot of his own
arm's length. But normal people according to the גמרא Gemara are three
אמות amot at least to their shoulders, which is standard Jewish height,
about four and a half feet. A normal person is how many
אמות? amot? Three. The גמרא Gemara says three אמות, amot, right? Which
is about four and a half, whatever, five feet to the person's
shoulders. So if משה Moshe is ten אמות, amot, we're not saying,
the גמרא Gemara is assuming we don't mean ten אמות amot of
normal people, we mean ten of his own אמות. amot. So therefore
he's disproportionate to his limbs. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, so
אמר ליה, amlei, so אמר ליה שימי, amlei Shimi, שימי Shimi that's
a question again we have the
שימי. Shimi. באמה של קרש קאמר. be'amah shel keresh ka'amar. No, he's
ten אמות amot of standard אמות, amot, of the אמה amah that
you use to measure the קרש. keresh. He's not disproportionate
to his own limbs.
Okay, he's
proportionate to his own limbs.
being small, we mentioned that there’s a problem of זרע של אהרן,
zera shel Aharon, right? Yeah, we mentioned the midget. But then,
apparently, yeah, that’s a little bit strange, right, that a midget was
but a giant is not.
All right, but if we’re focused on distractions, right, that would be
the ultimate.
I know, I know. So that’s what I said, you know, you’re
really, it’s really not being defined here as distraction. That’s what you
define in terms of כהנים kohanim for ברכת כהנים, birchas kohanim, but
not the actual. That was my point at the beginning. The actual
מום mum we see that that’s not really the criteria.
What if someone is exceptionally ugly? You know, did we get to
that?
Okay. Well, I told you that’s not quantifiable. What?
During ברכת כהנים birchas kohanim
you’re not supposed to look at them. Right,
that’s true.
That’s true.
Also you’re not supposed to like look directly at them anyway, ברכת
כהנים. birchas kohanim. Okay.
All right.
תנא, Tanna, well with ברכת כהנים, birchas kohanim, it’s like when you’re
doing a קרבן.
korban. No, no, I know, but I’m saying by ברכת כהנים birchas
kohanim it’s less about formal מום mum and it’s more about things
that are
just distractions. But so yes, why the point why that’s supposed to
be an issue if you’re not supposed to look at them, but
maybe you’re not supposed to look at them as they’re giving the
ברכה, bracha, maybe you looked at them before they began it. I
don’t know, it’s a good point. תנא כעצבע קטנה. Tanna ke'etzba ktana.
Okay. So חוטמו גדול chotmo gadol how big? כעצבע קטנה ke'etzba ktana
like a pinky, like a small finger, which again I don’t know
if that means that that’s first of all is that talking about
that it’s that much protruding? Is it that רש"י Rashi says it’s
the width of a small finger. רש"י Rashi says you’re one width
of a small finger beyond the average. Okay, which so much for
like Jewish noses or whatever, beyond the average Jew I guess what
the range of the average is, I don’t know. והצמיח והצמיאה vehatzimach
vehatzimiah which has to do with like this cauliflower ear, the particularly
small ear. תנא אף הצמיח, Tanna af hatzimach, even a צמיח. tzimach.
לא ידעי רבנן מאי צמיח, lo yad'ei Rabbanan mai tzimach, they didn’t
know what צמיח tzimach was. שמעוהו לההוא טייעא, shamu'ei lehahu taya'a, the
גמרא Gemara has this where they find out what words mean by
listening to these Arab traders or not, it’s more like merchants, but
which also speaks to you know, it’s precursor to the whole academic
study of Semitic languages, right? Because presumably they weren’t speaking Hebrew, but
they knew but you know, but they knew Arabic and they were
using their knowledge of Arabic to interpret משנה Mishnaic words. Okay. דהוה
קאמר מאן בעי צמיח, Dehava ka'amar man ba'ei tzimach, who wants a
צמיח? tzimach? What’s he selling? ואשתכח גדיא חזיזא, ve'ishtakach gadya chaziza, they
found a very hairy goat, presumably which also had like very big
ears. I the hair seems to be incidental. So basically צמיח tzimach
means that it has particularly long ears, large ears. אמר רב חסדא
עז שאין לה קרנים, Amar Rav Chisda ez she'ein la karnayim, now
that we’re talking about goats,
if a goat does not have horns, ורחל שיש לה קרנים, verachel
sheyesh la karnayim, or a sheep has horns, כשר לגבי מזבח, kasher
legabei mizbe'ach, it’s not even a מום, mum, okay? Even though that’s
obviously not normal for them. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we
taught similarly, יש דברים שהם כמומין ואינם כמומין, yesh devarim shehem kimumin
ve'einam kimumin, ושוחטים עליהם במקדש אבל לא במדינה, veshochatin aleihem bamikdash aval
lo bamedina, there’s things that you might think are מום mum but
they aren’t, and you can even bring them as a קרבן korban
in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and you can’t, it’s not a
basis for שחיטה shechting outside, which almost goes without saying. ואלו הן
ve'elu hen and these are they: עז שאין לה קרנים, ez she'ein
la karnayim, if a goat doesn’t have horns, ורחל שיש לה קרנים,
verachel sheyesh la karnayim, or a sheep has horns, והצמיח והצמיח והצומח.
vehatzimach vehatzimach vehatzome'ach. Now
and the צמיח, tzimach, צמיח tzimach and צומח, tzome'ach, now that’s quite
interesting, right? Because in our משנה Mishna those actually were considered to
be a מום mum and here we’re saying that by animals they’re
not. But this actually points to the גמרא’s Gemara whole point that
there’s a whole range of things or the משנה’s Mishna point that
are problems by humans and not problems by animals. Okay, so yes,
by animals these things would be, are not problematic, we have a
narrower definition and we don’t have this concept of זרע של אהרן,
zera shel Aharon, but these are a problem by humans. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. והצומח אמר רב חסדא אמר
אמימר, vehatzome'ach amar Rav Chisda amar Ameimar, נטלו קרנותיה וזכרותן עמהן פסולה.
nitlu karnoteha vezachrutan imahen pesula.
So that’s if it never had a horn. Let’s say it had
a horn and the horn was taken off with the marrow, the
זכרות. zachrut. Now the זכרות, zachrut, רש"י Rashi says apparently the way
a horn grows is that there’s some central part of it that
actually has marrow and then there’s like a lot of horn or
whatever bone around it that grows around it that doesn’t. So if
the horn was actually removed, not just it didn’t grow with it,
with the marrow part, with the inner bone that had the marrow,
then that is פסולה. pesula. פסולה ואין פודין עליה, Pesula ve'ein podin
aleiha, but you can’t redeem the animal if it’s a בכור, bechor,
it’s enough of a problem that you don’t bring it as a
קרבן korban but not enough that you can redeem it outside the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. נטלו טלפיהם וזכרותן עמהן, nitlu telafayahem vezachrutan imahen,
if the hooves are removed
with the inner marrow bone, פסולין ופודים עליהם, psulin ufodin aleihem,
that’s a bigger problem and you can even redeem it. I have
no idea. מיתיבי, Meiseiv, it’s more unusual, it’s more visible, I really
don’t know. נטלו קרניה וטלפיה וזכרותן עמהן, nitlu karneha utelafaya vezachrutan imahen,
the ברייתא braisa says that if the, this is about a פרה
אדומה, parah adumah, that if the or not if whatever normal קרבן,
korban, if the horns or the hooves are removed with the marrow
bone inside, פסולין ופודים עליהם, psulin ufodin aleihem, you can redeem, so
how do you say we don’t redeem, so that it’s not a
big enough מום? mum? לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא דאיעקר איעקור ha
de'i'akar i'akur
One is that it was totally torn, taken out by the root,
the other is that it was cut down but the sort of
the base is still there. So it's a question if the base
is still there, it's not such a by the horns on the
head
you can't- it's not a big enough of a מום mum and
you can still redeem it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says,
ודאיגום איגומי פסול v'd'igum igumei pasul and if it was just cut
down without being torn, taken out by the roots, is that invalid?
So the גמרא Gemara says,
ורמינהי, v'remihu, פרה שקרניה וטלפיה שחורים. parah shekarnaiha utlafaiha shchorim. Here's where
you can fix a מום. mum. This is although it isn't a
מום, mum, there's a problem with the פרה parah being תמימה tmimah
fully red. Let's say you have a פרה parah that the horns,
the tip of the horns are black or the tip of the
hooves are black. That's a problem that it's not אדומה תמימה adumah
tmimah although normally those aren't red, but anyway somehow the blackness is
a problem by the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So what do you
do? יגוז yigoz so you cut it off, cut off the tip
of the horn, cut off the tip of the- of the thing.
So you see if you cut it off that it's actually not
a problem at all. So how can you say it's enough of
a problem that you don't bring it as a קרבן, korban, presumably
it's the same standard by a פרה אדומה? parah adumah? So תרגמה
זעירי targema Zeiri מעילא דשחור. meila deshachor. No, when you cut it
off above the marrow, the very tip, like you give it like,
you know, you give it like you cut its toenails. Like if
you cut off the very tip it's not a problem at all.
If you cut it off with the marrow but you haven't uprooted
it, it's enough of a מום mum that you don't bring it
as a קרבן korban and if you uprooted it then you can
even redeem it outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So we're a
little going back to some earlier examples by animals. Now we turn
to the next משנה Mishnah which gets us into a whole fascinating
discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look and try to
get to the next משנה. Mishnah. דדין שוכבין כשל אשה. dadin shochvin
keshel isha.
So the כהן Kohen has large breasts like a woman's breasts, you
know that they basically, you know, that they lay- they flap down
on the on the torso.
כרסו צבה, kriso tzava, he has a blown up belly. Not just
fat. Not fat, right, there's obviously some type of a, you know,
some type of a condition. טיבורו יוצא, tiburo yotzei, talk about things
that are not visible. He's got an outie belly button. What is
the occurrence of outie belly buttons? That's got to be pretty common.
Right? Yeah. Well, it may mean like
particularly protruding.
One in thirty-four. Like what?
One in thirty-four?
Somebody's got to be able to check that out.
What? The opposite of the measure, you know, got to be very
small.
Very small, yeah. I don't know. Anyway, that seems particular- I mean
talk about something that's not visible and that's actually what you would
think within the normal distribution, right? נכפה, nichpeh, if somebody has epilepsy
אפילו אחת לימים, afilu achat l'yamim, even if it's only in rare
times. Now that again, talk about something that's not visible, right? That's
just a medical condition. So again, now again we're not calling it
a מום, mum, might be calling it זרעו של אהרן, zaro shel
Aharon, but now this concept of זרעו של אהרן, zaro shel Aharon,
right, is even things that are not about aesthetics, right? Unless you're
saying, well since it will happen once when he's doing the עבודה
avodah it becomes part of the experience of the עבודה, avodah, that
could be the idea.
But Rashi says פעם אחת לימים שיש לו זמן קבוע. pa'am achat
l'yamim sheyesh lo zman kavua. You're saying like you actually have epilepsy
at a fixed day of the year?
No, no, no, no. אלא פעם שבאה לו. ella pa'am sheba lo.
Oh,
I don't know.
What does
that mean?
No, שאינו נופל אלא פעם אחת. she'eino nofel ella pa'am achat. No,
I didn't understand that. I just meant it was very rare, it
only occurs rarely. Okay,
infrequent. Okay. He said fixed.
They're saying fixed. He said fixed. I was actually fixed and infrequent.
I know, but fixed and infrequent.
I know, that's the way רש''י Rashi says. Okay. I don't know
that that is the necessary- I don't necessarily know that that's- that's
רש''י. Rashi. I'm just saying I don't know in the פשט pshat
of the משנה, Mishnah, but okay. But anyway you are right, it
is רש''י, Rashi, okay. רש''י Rashi says it's infrequent but it's fixed.
But you could just say it's whatever, it's rare.
Yeah, I was just questioning a statistical pamphlet that looked at frequency
of seizures,
we did not find a single patient with periodic seizures. They're either
clustered or completely random, never periodic.
Right. And I don't understand why periodic would be significant here. If
anything, it's the fact if it's periodic then don't do the עבודה
avodah that day. Maybe it's a חידוש, chiddush, even if it's periodic
even though you could avoid doing the עבודה avodah that day. Anyway,
all right. Anyway what? Ten percent? Ten percent is outies? You just
look that up? Okay, so all right. So you know that's pretty-
if it's so rare to find, right, but
we've now eliminated ten percent of the population. No, most of these
are not- that's true, but most of these are I would say
less than one percent, but outies that it's a מום mum at
all and I mean not even a שוה בזרעו. shaveh b'zaro. All
right, we'll get to that. I am, okay, it's a good question.
Maybe that'll be a nice experiment, a nice like assignment, a home
assignment for the reader at home. Okay anyway, let's- but particularly to
me it's not what bothers me is not how many people- well,
here the question is just that conceptually we're calling something that ten
percent that is very non-visible, that looks very natural and that we're
calling this a שוה shaveh even not a... even not a ממש,
mamash, a שבר בזרוע של אהרן. Shever bazroah shel Aharon. And also,
the idea here of epilepsy is also something that's not visible, unless
the fact that it's possibly will occur during the עבודה avoda makes
it considered visible. רוח צרה בא אליו, Ruach tzarah ba eilav, which
רש״י Rashi says צרה tzarah might be the name of a שיד,
sheid, but the best explanation here I think is just
as תוספות Tosafot says, it means right,
it means asthma, asthma. So, asthmatic, המושפן ובעל גבר. hamushpan u'baal gever.
מושפן mushpan means very large testicles, and בעל גבר baal gever means
a very large male genitalia,
right. אמר רב אבא בריה דרב חייא בר אבא. Amar Rav Abba
breih d'Rav Chiya bar Abba. Okay, now that we're in that topic,
but actually not by the end of the משנה, mishna, now focusing
on the beginning about bloated stomach. משתינין מים בפני רבים. Mashtinin mayim
bifnei rabbim. You can urinate in front of other people, you don't
have to worry about privacy, because the גמרא Gemara as we'll see
understood that a person that needs to urinate, a man that needs
to urinate and doesn't, that it could actually cause the person some
serious injury, medical conditions. So therefore you don't hold it in, you
got to go, you got to go, even if there are people
around. ואין שוסין מים בפני רבים, Ve'ein shosin mayim bifnei rabbim, and
you don't drink in front of people. Now, תוספות Tosafot is actually
interesting, תוספות Tosafot says it sounds like it means yeah, you shouldn't
eat in public. Although if you read this little תוספות, Tosafot, it's
clear, no, it's clear that תוספות Tosafot had a problem with that,
that actually in France, you know, I think that there's stories about
in France anyway, they would have like, you know, picnics in public
and the whole thing. So תוספות Tosafot tries to reinterpret what this
means. He says well, maybe that's only water, but like wine, that
you can drink in public. Or תוספות Tosafot says maybe it means
even somebody that is so modest that would be even, even the
type of person that wouldn't drink in public should not, can go
ahead and urinate in public, okay, because it's so medically urgent.
ותניא נמי הכי, Ve'tanya nami hachi, we
taught similarly: משתינין מים בפני רבים ואין שוסין מים בפני רבים. Mashtinin
mayim bifnei rabbim ve'ein shosin mayim bifnei rabbim. Sounds like you're not
supposed
to drink. ומעשה באחד שביקש להשתין מים, U'maaseh be'echad she'bikesh l'hashtin mayim,
somebody needed to urinate, ולא השתין, ve'lo hishtin, and
נמצא כריסו צבה ve'nimtza kriso tzeva and that's how it fits into
our משנה. mishna. His stomach bloated as a result. Okay, so at
least that's what the גמרא Gemara attributed it to. In a minute
we'll see the גמרא Gemara will question that diagnosis. Now, however, we're
going to digress a little bit and talk about
this point that you got to urinate when you have to.
There's stories in the גמרא Gemara about it.
We're about to read those stories. Here's where they are.
שמואל אצטריך ליה בשבתא דריגלא. Shmuel itztarech lei be'shabta de'rigla. So שמואל
Shmuel had to urinate and it was the שבתא דריגלא shabta de'rigla
which means it was in the period before the ריגלא regla where
he was giving a public lecture to masses of hundreds of people
but he had to go to the bathroom. So what did he
do? Urinate, specifically. Defecate, the גמרא Gemara would never say, but urinate
is where it's saying this.
נדלו ליה גלימא, Nadla lei glima, they spread out some cloth, some,
you know, some cloak to give him some privacy and he urinated
and then they took it down and he continued to give his
דרשה. drasha. אתא לקמיה דאבוה, Ata lekamei d'avuha, he went to his
father, אבוה דשמואל avuha d'Shmuel is sometimes, you know, an אמורא Amora
in his own right. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he told him the
story. So then he said back to him,
אמר ליה, amar lei, or it's implicit that he told him the
story and then אמר ליה amar lei his father said to him,
אייתי לך ארבע מאה זוזי, ayei lach arba me'ot zuzei, I will
give you four hundred זוז, zuz, וזיל אהדר עובדא, ve'zil ahar uvda,
but go reverse what you've done. Okay, go teach people the opposite,
that they shouldn't learn from your lesson, because now people will think
that they should, that they need privacy and that will lead to
people that don't have that opportunity to actually endangering themselves.
את דאפשר לך, At d'efshar lach, you, it was possible for you
to get privacy and to do it within a second's time. דלא
אפשר ליה, Delo efshar lei, מסתכן, mistakein, somebody who doesn't have that
opportunity, doesn't have a cloak available to them or whatever, doesn't have
people ready to spread out the cloak, you know, people that don't
have that opportunity, they're going to learn from your lesson and they're
going to wait until they're in private and they're going to endanger
their health. Now, it's actually interesting that רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says,
so what does it mean reverse the actions? רש״י Rashi says go
back and give them a דרשה drasha and tell them you're not
supposed to wait. But רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom actually says, you know,
it's very hard because what you do is often so much more
powerful than what you say. So רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says is,
next time you give the דרשה, drasha, I want you to make
a point of urinating publicly in front of them so that they
can learn from your action, the action will negate your previous action.
Did you know women came to those שבתא דריגלא? shabta de'rigla? Uh-huh,
interesting.
It was ילתא Yalta with the way
it was prepared.
I don't remember that story. Uh-huh. שבתא דריגלא Shabta de'rigla so in
front of women, in public? Women are walking? Apparently.
Well, look,
we will see that in a minute. It was like public.
Wouldn't they just urinate underneath their robe? They wouldn't expose themselves.
Well, why did they cover him up?
What? רב זירא, Rav Zeira, I mean, you don't have to be,
I mean, you can maybe turn to the side and try to
get a certain amount of privacy, but still they
consider urination immodest.
Anyway, here is what רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says: שתשתין לפניהם בגלויא
כדי שלא ילמדו ממך. She'tashtin lifneichem begaluya kedei shelo yelmedu mimcha.
Okay. So which by the way I think points to, it's very
important because what do you mean תהדר עובדא? ta'er uvda? Right, it's
always like, you know, they write a full page story in the
paper and then they have a
two-line correction buried somewhere in, right? So you did a big public
action and now you're going to give a דרשה, drasha, nobody's going
to remember. Remember, you know, so it's very, I think it's interesting
that רש״י Rashi like you know did not take רבנו גרשום, Rabbeinu
Gershom, but רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom I think is the more powerful
reading here. Do an action that is opposite to the other action
that you just did. Okay, now we're going to have talking about
women, here's another story.
מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi אצטריך אגודא דגמלא. itztreich
aguda degamla. מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi had to
urinate when he was right by like the bridge of a river
and he had nowhere to go. So it's a river, something. Okay,
anyway, or the whatever,
אשתין, ashtin, he urinated. אמרו ליה, amru lei, so they said to
him, חמתך קאתיא, khamatakh ka'atya, your mother-in-law is coming, I mean she
might have seen you. אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them,
באודנה, be'udna, I would even do it in her ear.
Which means it's pretty, pretty, what's the word here, yucky, gross, but
within
earshot. What you think it means, it should have said, it should
have said within eyesight. Anyway, but it means I don't care, I
go where I have to go, I don't want to endanger myself
and I don't care who else is around. Okay, but it was
a bit, not the most respectful way of saying it. Okay, but
now the גמרא Gemara leaves that and goes back to the person
whose stomach bloated and says how do you know it bloated because
of the urination, maybe it bloated טיפיקא משום עלקא, tipika mishum alka,
maybe because of some other type of impurities in the water, maybe
something else caused the person impurities like the, what do you call
it, parasite, thank you. So the גמרא Gemara says בשותת, beshotet, no,
it wasn't just that his stomach bloated but also that he could
not, when he would urinate it would not come out in a
stream, it would just drip. So it was clear that it had
to do with urinating. So let's just finish this. תנו רבנן, tanu
rabanan, שני נקבים יש בו באדם. shnei nekavim yesh bo ba'adam. People,
a human, a man really means a man, has two holes.
אחד מוציא שתן ואחד מוציא שכבת זרע. ekhad motzi sheten ve'ekhad motzi
shikhvat zera. I'll talk about the actual biology in a minute. One
from which urine comes out, the other from which semen comes out.
ואין בין זה לזה אלא כקליפת השום. ve'ein bein zeh lezeh ela
keklipat hashum. They're only separated by a thin membrane that's like a,
like a garlic paper, you know garlic paper, you know how thin
that is, right, the shell of a garlic. בשעה שאדם נצרך, besha'ah
she'adam nitzrakh, and a person needs to urinate, אם ניקבו זה לתוך
זה, im nikvu zeh letokh zeh, נמצא עקר. nimtza akar. If they
were,
because he withheld his urination, if that led for a hole to,
you know, to be formed between this membrane that separates, then it's
going to get into his seminal, you know, tube and therefore he
will become, he will become sterile. So the גמרא Gemara understood not
only was it a problem about the stomach bloating, it could lead
to sterility. Now, what actually is, is that the semen feeds in
into the, into the, what do you call, not a tube, what
do you call it, the vas deferens gland?
Anyway, it feeds in inside the body, it comes from a different
tube but that tube feeds in to the tube through which obviously
the urine comes and they're never like parallel and separate. It's just
a separate tube that feeds in and then they both come out.
Now it could be that the גמרא Gemara got to this by,
I don't know, I'm just speculating, they might have gotten it from
Galen's anatomy. I didn't check Galen's anatomy, it's quite possible, but whoever
it was, it could also have been from an analogy to women,
right, that the orifice for the urine is different than the orifice
for sex. So it could be that they made a similar assumption
for men that there were the two separate orifices. Anyway, I know
it's 8:30 but maybe we'll just do a little bit more just
at least finish this concept here. So let's take a look. אמר
ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, מאי דכתיב, mai dikhtiv, what's meant by
the verse, לא יהיה בך עקר ועקרה ובבהמתך, lo yihyeh bekha akar
va'akarah uvivehemtekha, you shall have no sterile in you and in your
animals. אימתי לא יהיה בך עקר, eimatai lo yihyeh bekha akar, when
will you not have become sterile? בזמן שבבהמתך, bizman shebevehemtekha, if you
act like an animal, if you're prepared to urinate in public, then
that will prevent you from becoming, obviously you don't have to, it's
not a מצוה, mitzvah, but don't let that be a restraint. Is
that הלכה? halakha? Apparently. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, amar Rabi Yehoshua
ben Levi, לא יהיה בך עקר, lo yihyeh bekha akar, he translates
the whole thing more religiously rather than biologically. Do not be an
עקר, akar, you know, sterile, מן התלמידים, min hatalmidim, doesn't mean children,
it's now a religious context, meaning make sure you have students, the
idea that students are like children. ועקרה, va'akarah, so what does it
mean a woman's being sterile? שלא תהא תפילתך עקורה, shelo tehei tephilatkha
akurah,
your prayer should not be sterile, should be answered. How do you
ensure that your prayer should be fertile, should lead to God answering
it? לפני המקום. liphnei hamakom. אימתי, eimatai, when do you achieve that?
בזמן שאתה משים עצמך כבהמה. bizman she'atah mesim atzmekha kevehemah. If you
make yourself lowly like an animal, you're humble when you pray, then
that leads to it being fertile, it being answered by God. Okay.
אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, לא ישתין אדם מים לא בכלי
חרס ולא על מקום קשה. lo yashtin adam mayim lo bikhli kheres
velo al makom kasheh. You should not urinate on top of pottery
vessels or on top of hard ground. Why? Because when they, not
on, in pottery vessels, because
they would take it and pour it into the river. And the
hard ground, we would see would flow into the river. And why
is that a problem?
דאמר רב היני רב, de'amar Rav Heini Rav, הני מדורי ד hanei
madurei de these inclines of בבל Bavel מהדרי מיא לניחותן. mahadri maya
l'inhitan. Ultimately the water goes from off the hard ground or it's
poured from these pottery into the rivers, and the rivers feed and
they or they incline the ground inclines into into the rivers and
then it feeds into עין עיטם, Ein Eitam, which is the water
you use in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So you don't want to
be doing that.
תוספות Tosafot says, you're polluting your rivers is what they're saying.
You're polluting your rivers, but particularly the rivers of ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. תוספות Tosafot says it sounds like the rivers of בבל Bavel
flow into ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the Euphrates flows into ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. He said but I asked somebody from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and they told me that it's the opposite, that the that
the Euphrates flows into
בבל, Bavel, not from בבל Bavel to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but
the opposite way. So he leaves it as a question. Okay, אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, האי איתתא, hai iteta, that's let's just get to
the judas, a woman, although we said all this by men, that
even in front of women, a woman
לא תקומה להדיא באנפי ינוקא אגיסא lo takuma lahadi b'anpei yanuka agisa
בהדיא ינוקא, bahadya yanuka, she not urinate in front of in front
of even in front of children. Okay, and the why is it
different? So either the גמרא Gemara understood that it was not two
things, one of two things maybe both, that it was not as
much of a medical concern for women, they understood had to do
with the their understanding of male biology, or and or number two,
that it was less acceptable or less normal for women to expose
themselves even to urinate as it was societally for men to do
so. But what is he saying? So as I'm saying maybe they
only thought it was dangerous for men. אגיסא, Agisa, but if she
moves over to a side, לית לן בה, leit lan bah, it's
not a problem. תני Tani תנא tana in a ברייתא Braita רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, עמוד החוזר amud
hachozer מביא את האדם לידי הדרוקן. mavi et ha'adam lidei hadrokan. If
you hold back a defecating, then that leads to הדרוקן, hadrokan, which
is I forget, some type of sickness, I forget what it was.
חולי מעיים, choli me'ayim, רש״י Rashi says some type of digestive problem
or whatever. סילון החוזר, silon hachozer, if you hold back urinating, מביא
את האדם לידי ירקון, mavi et ha'adam lidei yarkon, it brings to
jaundice. אמר רבא בר רב הונא Amar Rava bar Rav Huna אמר
רב, amar Rav, כטינא אמר ריש לקיש, ketina amar Reish Lakish, דם
רבה שחין רבה. dam raba shechin raba. If you have too much
blood, you haven't let blood too much frequently enough, that leads to
boils and blisters. שכבת זרע רבה, shichvat zera raba, if you have
too much too much semen, you haven't had sex frequently enough with
your wife, צרעת רבה, tzara'at raba, that leads to leprosy. צואה רבה,
tzoa raba, if you have too
much feces, thank you, you haven't gone to the bathroom, you haven't
defecated, הדרוקן רבה, hadrokan raba, that leads to this illness of הדרוקן.
hadrokan. מי רגלים רבים, mei raglayim rabim, if you have too much
urine, you don't you hold back your
urination, then ירקון רבה, yarkon raba, it leads to jaundice. And with
that we will end today since you
were always asking for stories.
I won't be story tonight.
I'll show
you story tomorrow.